When I was in Afghanistan, every every
day when we went on a mission, anything
bad that came of it, we chocked it to
like we're working for a better
tomorrow, for a better future, for our
our our or our or our or our or our or
our or our or our or our or our or our
or our our comrade, our soldiers, our
you know, our battle buddies who died
there. We were we we thought this we
were doing this for a better tomorrow.
If we went to some Afghan's home and we,
you know, searched their house for
weapons or for somebody we were looking
for, we chocked it up to like, hey,
we're doing it for a better tomorrow.
We're doing for girls education. But
what happened today? And when I see
Afghanistan today, it infuriates me.
What did why did we do all of that if we
were just going to go back to the
Taliban that were there in the first
place?
Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus. Before we get started, I
wanted to ask you, as I usually do, if
you would do me a personal favor, and
that is if you enjoy this content,
please like, share, and most
importantly, subscribe. It really,
really helps us with the YouTube
algorithm and it helps us get the word
out. Well, I am very, very pleased today
to welcome Safi Raou to the show. Safi
has an amazing story. Safi's story in my
view is really the culmination of the
American dream. He was born in a refugee
camp in Pakistan in 1994 and then as a
teenager immigrated with his family to
the United States where he became later
on a hospital corman and a linguist for
the US Navy. Safi graduated from
Georgetown University on a premed track
and then was accepted to medical school,
but he elected to defer medical school
so that he could return to Afghanistan
to help people who needed the most help.
He founded Human First Coalition, which
works to evacuate refugees from
Afghanistan.
In December of 2021, while providing
humanitarian relief in Kabell, Safi was
detained by the Taliban and held for 105
days. He was subsequently released in
early April 2022 following negotiations
between the Taliban and the Biden
administration. Safi, welcome to the
show. You have a lot of guts and you
have that unique
that unique special thing where you feel
compelled to help people before helping
yourself. I want to first even before I
ask a question just say you have my
deepest respect and thanks for being on
the show.
>> Thank you John. Thank you for having me.
>> Pleasure is mine. and and likewise,
John, I've read your story and it's
incredible and uh you know, I applaud
everything you've done.
>> Thank you very much for saying that.
Thank you. Well, I want to start with
just a quick overview of Afghanistan.
The United States spent 20 years in
Afghanistan. We weren't wanted. We
weren't needed. We hadn't been asked to
rebuild the country after after the
initial response to the 911 attacks, but
we made a decision at least the Bush
administration and following subsequent
uh administrations made the decision to
go to Afghanistan to stay there and
unfortunately to kill or displace a lot
of people. So here we are 24 years
later.
tell us what Afghanistan is like today.
Is it better? Is it worse after the US
uh occupation?
>> It's it's a complicated question. Um if
we look at it what Afghanistan was 20 25
years ago. Um it was the infrastructure
or basically everything uh that we have
in the modern world that didn't exist.
it was almost if Afghanistan was living
a 10020 years in the past. Um today we
do see Afghanistan as a country that's
been rebuilt that has roads that has
infrastructure, electricity, internet,
uh people have access to the world,
people have access to Facebook, all the
social medias and they do get a lot of
their information from there. On the
other hand,
it's also far worse. In when we invaded
Afghanistan in in 2001, Taliban were
fighting with AK-47s and beat up uh
Hilux trucks. Today, they have over $90
billion worth of military equipment.
That includes Humvees, that includes
MRAPs, that includes planes, that
includes M4s, all our modern technology
or modern weapons. So
what if if you look at Afghanistan when
Taliban first came on August 15, 2021
and you compare that to today,
you see the the the downward spiral of
Afghanistan into more um people are
becoming more conservative pe the
especially the Taliban fighters, they're
becoming more conservative. there's
more. Uh, so we can't see it right now,
but what is Afghanistan going to become
in the next 10 years?
>> You know, this is something I struggle
with and I'm glad to have you on the
show because you're not just
Afghan-American. You have worked and
lived in Afghanistan and you've seen the
ugly side of Afghanistan. So I I've come
to say that
that the Taliban did not descend on
Afghanistan from the moon and come down
and you know out of from outer space to
to settle Afghanistan. These are the
these are the the fathers, the the
brothers, the sons, the husbands of
Afghan women
um who have
taken over the leadership of the
country. The United States was there for
more than two decades. We gave the
Afghan people an idea of what a
westernstyle democracy looks like. They
didn't want a western style democracy.
There was no historical precedent in
Afghanistan for a western style
democracy. They had the Loya Jurga
system that they were happy with. Um and
in the west we looked at these well what
I would call atrocities that were being
committed by the the Taliban against the
Afghan people even against Afghan
history and heritage. let's say the
Bamian uh Buddhas for example,
but at the end of the day,
they chose the Taliban.
Can you explain that? I think this is
something that most Americans don't
fully understand.
>> Uh absolutely. This is exactly how I put
it. It's uh it's it's ironic that you
use the exact same words that Taliban
didn't come from like some outer space
other planet you know they they they are
from that land they are from Afghanistan
they are 99.9% of Taliban are from
Afghanistan they are those people and
when I say that
that's where we went wrong that's where
America went wrong you know in 200 until
2006 2007 there wasn't
uh a significant insurgency in
Afghanistan. Taliban laid down their
weapons, went to the mountains or to
their homes or to Pakistan.
What happened was America undermined the
Taliban or the people the people of
Afghanistan. They thought they're going
to go arrest, send them to Guantamo, uh
torture them, they're going to kill
their family members. and the people are
aren't going to do anything. Taliban
came back into existence because the
American atrocities becau became because
of the uh atrocities that the the
government that was installed by America
because of them. If you if you look at
um so I spent a lot of time at the uh US
embassy in in Kbble and I was with with
JC at the time and you know with the
with those teams we we used to go to the
annex which Ariana the CIA station there
and if you look at that geography the
station is basically inside the
presidential path.
So,
how ironic is it that the CIA station is
inside the presidential palace? So, who
is running the government
at the time when Carzi was the
president? And what he was trying to do
is
uh go and reach out to those people who
had started some insurgency and that
included Mullah brother that eventually
the US reached an agreement with him uh
the Doha agreement. He was trying to
reach out to him. But what happened you
know what happened there was Mullah
brother was arrested and put in jail.
Instead of him coming and Carzai they
sitting together and talking and
figuring out a way forward for the
country they arrested him. They tortured
him. He was in jail for many many many
years and eventually he was released at
the request of the American government
and he was flown to Doha and the
American
uh you know Mike Pompeo sat down with
him and reached an agreement without the
the the say of the Afghan people.
So you you you kind of think who was
running the government. Was it just a
puppet government in Afghanistan that
the CIA was running and doing whatever
they wanted to do? Um, so we go back to
that. We didn't involve the people of
Afghanistan in uh deciding what their
future is going to be. And you put it
exactly how I would put it. They didn't
come from Mars. They were living there.
Their families were there. Their houses,
their children, their parents, their
wives, all of them, they are from
Afghanistan. And
what we did is we chose one side and
completely ignored and brutalized the
other side. And that doesn't go well.
You can only push somebody so far.
>> It's exactly the same mistake we made in
Iraq in 2002 where as soon as we crossed
the border, we said that nobody who has
ever been a member of the Bath party may
participate in government. Well,
everybody was a member of the Bath Party
and most of them joined the Bath Party
because they were forced to. It was the
only way that they could work and earn
money to feed their families. We just
made it worse. I I wanted to ask you
too, I'm I'm still thinking of these
stupid mistakes that we made in
Afghanistan because we didn't understand
the culture and we didn't understand the
country's history. I remember I was
still at the CIA at the time where the
US military made a decision that it was
going to fight corruption in
Afghanistan. And so the way they were
going to do that was if you were a
member of a certain tribe or a certain
family, you were not permitted to serve
in the Afghan military or police in that
area. So if you were from Helmand
for example, they sent you to
Herat, right? Or you were from Kandahar,
they sent you to Jalalabad.
And what ended up happening is local
residents just said, "I don't know who
this guy is. He's not from this area.
He's not from my family. He's not from
my tribe. I'm not going to pay any
attention to him, and I'm not going to
do anything that he says." And Law and
Order fell apart. Am
I just
misremembering this or was this a
problem that led to bigger problems
visav law and order?
>> Absolutely. It was
you see even here let's take an example
of America right if we descend on
American cities and American towns with
with heavy military that is from another
state and we go to the everybody's homes
and round them up at in the middle of
the night people are not going to just
sit down and and watch that happen it's
an inherent quality or inherent um uh Uh
people don't just take and keep taking.
They at at some point they're going to
rise. And you said we made this mistake
in in Iraq. It's not just Iraq. Every
country we have ever gone to like go
back all the way back to uh Vietnam uh
Korea uh even you know in the 90s uh
during the Cold War every South American
country just the list goes on and on. We
don't go and
learn what the country is about and then
we we we figure out based we we used we
we involved those countries first of all
like when we were conducting operations
even we were conducting operations with
our partners uh that were the Afghan
military we didn't share intel with them
we were like oh this is you know top
secret SCI we can't share this with
or if we were I it's it's ridiculous.
It's their country. Um they know the
geography and and you are right.
Afghanistan has a very very specific
culture. It has very specific norms. And
for Afghan people, what is more
important than their life, it's their
dignity.
>> And and when you send somebody who is
who they don't know, they'll fight them.
They'll fight them till till death.
They're either going to win or die.
There is no option for them. If you send
some stranger that's going to just go
into their house. And we did that for 20
years. We'd go in the middle of the
night. They they're all sleeping.
Helicopters come in, you know, surround
the house. You go in, you turn their
house upside down, you harass their
woman, you harass their children, you
take their mail, and you know, three
days later, you release them because
they didn't do anything.
>> Absolutely. I've been on over a thousand
over a thousand missions in Afghanistan
over over a 4-year period with Rangers,
with Delta, with SEALs, and I almost 80%
of the missions that we went on, it was
just false false information. What
happens when you when you go to a
country that the people need desperately
need money? what they're gonna you you
tell them, hey, if you send us this
information, we're going to pay you this
much money and and what happens is
everybody is going to tattle on
everybody. It's either it's either for
money or personal grudges.
>> We filled Guantanamo with false
information.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. There's people
who spent a decade in Guantanamo and all
because of false information.
>> Yeah, that's exactly right. One of the
things that we saw here in the United
States in the immediate period before
sending combat forces into Afghanistan
was reporting about Afghan women and
girls being denied educations. They're
not allowed to read in public. They're
not allowed to sing. Uh they have to
have the permission of their father or
husband before leaving the house, etc.
Has any of that changed? Is this a new
more modern kind of Taliban or is this
the Moola Omar era Taliban just come
back to power?
>> It it's completely they're going back to
where they were.
>> Wow.
>> You know uh uh before 9/11
uh every all the schools that were built
by the US for the women, they have all
been closed. Women can't work. They
can't go outside the house. They are
making it
every day. It gets worse. That's what I
said is like
just comparing the Taliban that is today
to the Taliban from 2021 who made all
kinds of promises. What what happened
with Moola brother? Moola brother was
sort of the middle of the road sort of
uh he was going to compromise on some
things but they sidelined him. He was
supposed to be the leader of the Taliban
when we we we sent him to Kabell, but
now he's completely Awol. Uh and now the
Taliban who are ruling are from
Kandahar.
uh those Taliban that that are the
descendants of Moola Umar, the th those
who don't believe in uh girls education,
those who don't believe in women's
rights, those who don't believe in women
working, those who think that women
should stay at home and they're
basically just for bringing children.
That's that's what they think. And
that's the today's Taliban. Um and and
it's it's extremely concerning. And you
see when when when I was in Afghanistan,
every every day when we went on a
mission, anything bad that came of it,
we chocked it to like we're working for
a better tomorrow, for a better future,
for our our our or our or our our
comrade, our soldiers, our you know, our
battle buddies who died there. We were
we thought this we were doing this for a
better tomorrow. If we went to some
Afghan's home and we, you know, searched
their house for weapons or for somebody
we were looking for, we chocked it up to
like, hey, we're doing it for a better
tomorrow. We're doing for the girls
education. But what happened today and
when I see Afghanistan today, it
infuriates me. What did why did we do
all of that if we were just going to go
back to the Taliban were there in the
first place? And you know if if and
every every every every al-Qaeda member
that we we we look for eventually we
found them in Pakistan or we found them.
>> Oh, of course. Of course that I I made a
career out of hunting members of the
Taliban and al-Qaeda and every last one
of them was in Pakistan all the way up
to Osama bin Laden.
>> Exactly. and and they weren't just you
know sometimes they're like oh yeah
they're in the tribal areas and just you
know they are not they're sitting in
Islamabad they're in Rahul Pindi they
are in Lahore they are in in in Pashawar
you know I I went to school in Pakistan
>> every Friday every Friday prayer when
you would come out of the mosque right
outside there was somebody sitting uh
had their boxes open tens of people
collecting money for mujahedin for for
the fighters in Afghanistan, for
Taliban, for fighters in Kashmir, for
fighters in every every fight that was
being fought from a religious point of
view and
you you look at that and even today
we're like okay so what should we do
with Afghanistan? Let's ask Pakistan
and
it's just Afghanistan is a very complex
country. The people are very complex and
it needs complex solutions. It needs the
people who understand Afghanistan.
Afghanistan
back in the days when um there wasn't a
lot of transportation and uh people
weren't really mingling together. You
would go 30 minutes from your town, the
the next town, they were a completely
different people.
>> If you look at, you know, there's a town
that speaks Pashto. You drive 30
minutes, the next town they speak Farsy.
>> Yes.
>> The you drive another 30 minutes, they
speak Usbach. You drive another 30
minutes, they speak like Tajik, you go
they they speak uh, you know, Pashai,
which is, you know, in in eastern
southeastern Afghanistan. It's it's
crazy to think that you can go into a
country and just lump them into one
category and and think you can uh you
can change that. It's millions of
people. You can't just go and harass
people, brutalize them, and you think
the people are going to accept you,
>> especially a country like Afghanistan.
>> You know, before I get too far a field,
I I have to ask you about the recent um
border skirmish, I guess we could call
it, between Afghanistan and Pakistan. Uh
the the numbers of of people killed and
wounded varied wildly from as few as a
dozen to as many as 200. But the fact of
the matter is there was a lot of
shooting between Pakistani military and
uh and Afghan military. What happened to
relations between the two countries? How
did this this uh skirmish take place?
>> Well, it's been
it's a very long
>> Yeah. What surprised me when I was when
I was there was
in in what high esteem the Afghans held
the Indians but didn't say the same
thing about the Pakistanis.
>> Well, if you look at Pakistan, it it
only came into existence in 1947. It
didn't exist before that. And if you
look at it, when the Brits came to the
subcontinent, that whole area was called
the subcontinent. It included India,
current day India, Pakistan, Bangladesh.
It was a huge chunk of area. And when
the British decided to go further north
into Afghanistan, they they they they
got their asses beat.
>> Yes, they did.
>> You know, there were two Yeah.
Historically, they sent 200 British
soldiers. Every single one of them got
killed and they left one person alive.
They left one person alive who was a
surgeon. They left him alive who was
also shot in the leg. They let him live
and an Afghan uh person actually let him
uh live in his house. Gave him shelter
in his house and uh it was in Coast
Province. In coast province, an Afghan
let him into his house, nursed him back
to health, eventually dressed him in his
own clothes and smuggled him across the
border back to the his British uh
government.
So that's also things that Afghan people
do.
um uh you know Marcus Latrell who was uh
who was uh uh captured uh well his team
was killed in Afghanistan and he found
shelter in an Afghan person's home and
eventually uh he was rescued. So, so
those kind of things have happened
historically and well we are just
veering off the subject but what
happened the British what they did is
they basically told the that uh Amanu
Lahan was the the the person who they
was ruling Afghanistan at the time. They
made a pact with him. They were
basically like we are not gonna come
across the Durand line and you guys are
not going to come to the other side of
the Duran line and the Durand line was
named after the person who did the uh
the agreement. Well, what happened is
that agreement was uh set to be expired
in a 100red years and it did. So the
land that goes all the way to almost
bordering Islamabad and then on the qua
side as well this land all belong to
what was that day Afghanistan. So the
Afghans have never accepted that border.
uh and the people that live on both
sides, they share more with the Afghans
than they share with the Pakistanis that
who speak uh Uru that part of Pakistan
or they all speak Pashto. They have same
culture, they share they intermar with
each other, they have relationships,
they they are the same um lineage, same
tribes, but they're just divided by an
imaginary line
>> created by the British. created by the
British. And what happened there was
that those people because they also
share the same uh sort of culture, same
uh rules, the Pakistan didn't really
understand what to do with them. And for
the longest time, they were
self-governing.
They didn't send the military to to rule
that area. It's the the the village
elders, the village uh leaders, they
they were the ones ruling those areas of
Pakistan, the northwestern frontier
province. Uh it wasn't part of and it
wasn't it didn't belong to any um it
didn't belong to any of the provinces
either. It was uh it was uh federalized
lands that were self-governing.
But what happened after 911 is a lot of
the Taliban went to hide in those areas
with their relatives, with people they
knew. And
we we started drone strikes in those
areas and started killing people,
started, you know, doing drone strikes
on weddings, doing drone strikes on
family gatherings, on houses, funerals,
everything. And those people became fed
up and they started fighting back
against the Pakistani government. And
that's when the Pakistani government
sent their military
and the insurgency. I was actually in
Pakistan at that time and that's when
the insurgency started. That's when the
Pakistani the TTP the Talib the
Pakistani Taliban uh sort of came into
existence from a local sort of struggle
of the the people themselves. the Wazer
from Wazeristan from Ararachinar from
Kuram agency from agency they all
created small movements to fight against
the the Pakistani government and that is
going on till today. So what they do is
they Pakistan claims that some of those
leaders live in Afghanistan. So they
conduct air strikes in in in Afghanistan
and in most of those air strikes they
kill civilians and that's how it all
started and the Taliban were like we we
don't have air power we don't have long
long range missiles but we can fight on
the ground so they just went and they
couldn't be stopped. uh the Pakistan
can't Pakistan has a really really
strong military in terms of air power in
terms of long range missiles but they
can't fight uh the the the type of
guerrilla warfare that Afghanistan the
people of Afghanistan can do. So when
the Taliban started just going on the
ground and uh doing small groupoup
attacks, the Pakistani military was
taken by surprised and a lot of their uh
their their military posts were
overtaken by the Taliban. Um and then
what Pakistan did is they used
long-range missiles and air power to uh
conduct air strike on civilians on
homes. Um so it it's it's not that it
just came into existence. has existed
since the creation of Pakistan.
>> The Russian government announced
recently that it was preparing to
reestablish diplomatic relations with
Afghanistan, which is a a major move.
There are very very few countries around
the world that have a diplomatic
presence in Kabell. Um, for a fleeting
moment, Donald Trump toyed with the idea
publicly of reestablishing relations
with uh the Taliban. That has come to
nothing. It likely will come to nothing.
What do you think that this new
relationship between Russia and
Afghanistan means? And do you think
other countries especially countries
like uh Iran, like China, like India uh
will will normalize relations with uh
the Taliban?
>> Um you know, India has also said
recently that they're going to establish
diplomatic relations with Afghanistan.
In fact, reopen their embassy in in
Kabell.
>> And af and and uh ironically, Pakistan
was the first country who opened their
embassy in Kabell. and they still have
their embassy open in Kabell.
Um, Russia
has had presence in Kabell since the
beginning of the Taliban um since August
15.
It it's it's a very complicated
relationship between Russia and
Afghanistan.
Um, Russia
is Russia is in a bad place. Russia is
in a very bad place right now. And
Afghanistan is a country that
historically a lot of countries has
wanted to be present there. Um, the
Chinese are there right now, but the
Chinese
have a really complicated way of working
with different countries, especially
what they're doing in Africa, what
they're doing in Pakistan, what
Afghanistan is not like that. China goes
to a country, they're like, "We're going
to give you a billion dollars." But
they're not giving them a billion
dollars. They're basically buying
>> infrastructure their country. Yeah.
>> And that doesn't work with Afghanistan.
>> Yeah. it doesn't work. So, China figured
that out and they decided not to invest
in Afghanistan at all. So now
Afghanistan is going to Russia and they
have had talks for the last two three
years and you know Russia
if if they establish true real
relationship with Afghanistan.
Um it could be a good relationship for
both sides. Afghanistan has a lot of uh
natural resources that uh Russia really
needs right now and Afghanistan doesn't
have a lot of money, a lot of uh
equipment and they could be beneficial
to both sides but Afghanistan and Russia
has a very complicated relationship and
I don't think it's going to work out
between them. Um, and there is all the
all the other uh Russian uh the the
Russian countries that separated in the
'9s. All of those countries, Russia is
kind of getting more foothold in all of
those countries like Usbakistan,
Tajikistan, uh, Kyrgyzstan, um, all of
those countries. Russia is slowly
getting a foothold. They're sending
their troops there. Even when when the
Taliban took over uh August 15
uh of 2021, the border along the the
Tajjikstan border along uh northern
Afghanistan and along Usbekistsan,
the Russian soldiers came to secure
those borders. It wasn't the Tajjighstan
or Isbekiststan military themselves. The
Russian military came and secured that
border. So it it it tells that it kind
of shows how much control Russia has on
those neighboring countries to
Afghanistan.
So it's it's a Russian movement further
south getting more countries.
>> It seems to be more strategic in its
formulation than what the United States
has come up with. I I wanted to ask you
too about um was something that's been
very important in your life and it
continues to be and that's the situation
with the refugees. Um there are Afghan
refugees, thousands of Afghan refugees
who are um now being pushed out of Iran
back into uh Afghanistan. The the
Pakistanis have never wanted large
numbers of refugees in Pakistan and have
begun pushing them back into
Afghanistan. So, what's the situation
with refugees now? Is there really any
hope for them? Or do you think that for
the most part they'll be returned to
Afghanistan whether they like it or not?
>> Well, if you look at those refugees,
there's not just thousand, there's
millions about literally millions. Yeah.
1.4 million in Pakistan. And that's just
official numbers. There's more. Uh there
is over a few million in in Iran as
well. And if you look at these people,
they have been in those countries for
decades. They were all born in those
countries. The people who immigrated to
those countries, they're dead. It's
their children.
So Pakistan and Iran and most of the
countries in that region, almost all of
the countries in that region, when when
when you immigrate from another country
and you have children there, your
children don't automatically become
citizens.
>> That's right. There is no birthright
citizenship. there's no birthright
citizenship. You have to have uh uh you
have to have generation from going back
to hundreds of years uh in that country
in order to become a citizen of that
country. It does it doesn't just uh
happen if you're born there. So all
those children they don't even know
Afghanistan. Some of them don't even
speak
and they have gone to school there. They
have jobs there. They have businesses
there. If if you go to Lahore, some of
the biggest businesses in Pakistan are
owned by Afghan refugees. They have
clothing businesses that they import
from China and in Lahore they have the
biggest businesses. Similarly, in
Pakistan, they have some of the biggest
businesses there. They are billionaires,
millionaires that are Afghan refugees.
And what is happening right now is their
businesses are being uh taken from them
by force. and they're being sent back to
Afghanistan. Um, I think the biggest
issue with that is going to be for
Pakistan in Iran themselves. You know,
if you ask me about Pakistan, I know
every corner of Pakistan. I know every
street. I know every city. I know all of
their military garrisons. I know where
their ISI is. I know where uh their I
know where their their um nuclear
program is. And it's the cahoda which is
in the mountains going on the road from
Pashaw to Kuram agency that area they
have their nuclear program there. So all
of these refugees they know exactly
what Pakistan is their geography. So
sending them back to Afghanistan is a
really bad move on their part. It's if
if they lose everything they have in
Pakistan and they're sent to Afghanistan
with nothing and they have no way to
move forward, it's a very easy
recruiting uh population for TTP for the
Pakistani Taliban. Um and similarly for
Iran, it's a very easy tactic for the
Taliban to recruit them for all from all
different uh groups. uh al-Qaeda. It's a
it's a good recruiting uh tactic for
>> the Israelis recruited hundreds maybe
more than hundreds of Afghan refugees in
Iran to report back to them.
>> Absolutely. And you know those uh the
the people that we trained the the that
were trained by SEALs by by CIA that
were trained by Delta Force by Rangers
there were thousands of them. There were
thousands of special operations that we
trained and taught them how to use all
of our weapon systems. They can there
are easy recruits for for any
organization for even the Taliban that
are in power right now and some weapon
systems that they can't use can easily
be used in their intelligence department
in the Taliban intelligence department.
They weren't able to use a lot of the
sigant uh equipment that we had uh given
to them the CIA had given to them. um
the Taliban couldn't use that. But
eventually they learned because some of
the people that were working in the
previous government eventually had no
choice but to go and join the Taliban
and teach them how to use that.
>> You're exactly right. I'd like to I'd
like to ask you also about your own um
harrowing experience. Uh you had been
doing this kind of work for a long time.
You're there on the ground in
Afghanistan and then you're arrested.
Tell us about that. What that was like.
>> You know, it's being in in that
situation is I it's like uh I'm sure you
have your own experience, but it's being
taken against your will against and put
in a place that you have no idea what's
to become of you. you they they put a
you know they cover your face, they put
a bag on your head and you feel like
you're being you know paraded to your
execution and that was the fear every
day and
the the hardships on one side but what
you are thinking that whole time it's
more psychological than it's physical.
The physical is easy. That's not hard.
You get beaten up. You get uh it's cold.
The the you're sleeping on the bare
floor. You are tied or you have your
hands tied or all of that is easy. What
is hard is the psychological aspect of
it day in and day out. One, they don't
give you any information. They don't
tell you why you're there. They don't
tell you how long you're going to be
there. They don't tell you what you did
wrong. And
just you you are just there. You are at
their mercy
>> and you don't know if you're going to be
released next week or tried and
sentenced to 50 years in a dungeon
somewhere.
>> Absolutely. That's the number one uh
sort of psychological
u torture where you have no idea what
the future holds. Are you gonna be there
for a day or are you going to be there
for the rest of your life? And you know,
we did that to a lot of people. Uh we we
did that to a lot of people. The
director of intelligence who was holding
me um he would often come and u cuz I
was I didn't just sit there. I didn't
just sit and you know take their I I was
a fighter. I I like got up and fought
with all of them and I made their life
really hard.
So their chief comes down, the director
of intelligence, Abdul Hakasik, and he
comes to me and he's like, "Do you know
how long I was in Guantamo?"
He's like, "13 years."
He was in Guantanamo for 13 years. He
was released in exchange for Bober Bergd
Doll.
>> Oh my god.
So he was one of the five released in
exchange for Bo Bergd Doll. And he would
come down to me and he would often be
like, "Do you do you know what they did
to me?"
He's like, "They would release dogs on
us. They would like let the dogs uh bite
us." And he's like, "You are living you
are living the life. This is nothing."
And
sometimes I would think about that. I I
was and my argument was you guys were in
in in a war with a country. Today you
have signed an agreement with that
country and as a citizen of that country
you have no right to hold me. You held
Bob Bergdoll for many years. Um you you
you you uh held uh fer farer for for two
three years. You held many many American
soldiers for many years and that was
justified. That was you were fighting
with a country. They were holding you.
You were holding their people. But today
you've signed a peace deal and you have
you can no longer hold me. Um
they in order to calm me down, they
would often send these people who had
spent time in American prisons and they
would talk to me and they would tell me
about their time. Um and
you kind of humanize them. It it it they
become human to you. They become real.
You know, when I was fighting in uh with
with with Jak in Afghanistan,
I didn't think Taliban were real. They
they didn't feel real people. They
didn't feel like they were um existing
as humans. They were,
you know, it was just we thought there
were like maybe five, six thousand of
them and there were five, six in every
little village and they were just trying
to fight with us. But when I went to
Kbble and I saw their organized
soldiers like full thousands of military
fully trained and were able to stand
like soldier stands I was taken so far
back I was my mind couldn't comprehend
that it was how did these people have
organized thousands thousands of
soldiers
when we were claiming that we have
pushed all of them out of Afghanistan.
Where were their training centers? How
these people were training? Who trained
them specifically? Who trained them? who
I saw these guys like wearing our
helmets with night vision goggles and
the weapons the the M4s that had uh
sights on them, the night vision sights
and the and they were using them as if
they have been using them for many many
years. And I I I in in that place I
learned so much about the Taliban. Um,
you know, I went on a hunger strike for
for 9 days and that was an an
interesting experience with them as
well. The Taliban didn't want me to die.
>> I'm sure
>> they they wanted me to stay alive
and be a a token for uh the the Taliban
to uh you know negotiate with the
Americans. And Taliban were very
curious. They were they couldn't figure
out who I was. But what was really
interesting to them is everybody was
asking about me. You know, the Biden
administration was asking directly, it
was coming down directly from the
president and they were asking the
Taliban about me and asking them to
release me and they kept looking at who
I was. They looked at everything. Um
there were a lot of interesting things
that actually happened and one of the
most interesting thing is so they they
first day when they were going through
all my stuff one of the Taliban guy he
pulls out my wallet and he's going
through all my IDs and stupidly he pulls
out one of the ID it's my Navy ID it's
my military it's my uh CAC and he looks
at it then he looks at me. He kind of
smirks, puts it back, puts away my
wallet, and I never see that again.
>> What in the world?
>> So, this guy doesn't take this military
ID that has my picture, that has my
name, that clearly says I am an, you
know, um, unformed uh, uniformed forces.
And he puts it away. I never see that
again. He doesn't give it to his
superiors. He doesn't give it to another
Taliban guy. He doesn't tell a soul. He
puts it back, closes my wallet, and puts
it away in a drawer. And when I'm
leaving, he gives the wallet back
directly to me.
And I leave. And I'm like,
did this guy just help me? And why? And
why?
>> Why?
>> Why did he help me? Was it just a human?
Was it just being a human? and he just
wanted
that I don't get in more trouble or was
there something more?
>> So tell us a little bit about the
conditions in which you were held. Were
you treated with respect at least?
>> So it was everybody was different. There
were people who were very disrespectful
who were who were calling me a traitor,
who were calling me CIA agent, who were
calling me uh all kinds of things. They
thought I was a spy. I was working for
the CIA. I was and then there were those
that I became very I I started
connecting with them. I started uh
learning about them, about their
families. U so the the senior guard who
was for my prison um he was a older
probably his his late 20s and I asked
him I was are you married do you have
children he's like I just got married
but I don't have children I like why do
you not have children he's like oh well
I was a suicide bomber and um my turn
never came
>> so I wasn't I didn't want to marry
because I was suic I was going to go
conduct a suicide
>> that's very thoughtful of him
>> yeah but my turn never came and now that
we uh I don't need to be a suicide
bomber anymore. That's why I got married
and now I'm going to have children.
>> And it it was you learned about these
people. You you would think that a
suicide bomber would be some strange guy
who's out of their mind who has like no
sort of you know control of his own
thoughts or body or his own uh actions.
No, it's just a normal guy. a normal guy
would like, you know,
just believes in it.
>> Yeah. Right.
>> Um and yeah, so I was living in a
basement for uh the entire time we were
in a basement that was uh about 12 ft
below ground. Uh and I didn't see the
sun for about 70 days.
And finally when the negotiation was
going farther, they started taking us
out into the sun because they were like,
"We don't want you to look too pale when
you guys get out of here so you don't
look bad. You so so people don't think
that we were like keeping you in a
basement." Uh it was one of the
facilities of the uh back in the days uh
it was called NDS, which is the National
Directorate of Security that CIA
directly trained and equipped and worked
with. It was that department. Now it's
called the um uh now it's just called uh
director of intelligence. Uh so that's
where I was held in a basement. It's
>> it's inside that uh that that green zone
which also includes the presidential
palace
>> uh the CIA annex which was called Ariana
or the CIA annex. um and also very close
to the US embassy. Uh and it was in a
basement um the entire time I was there.
And you know, eventually we um bribed
one of the guards who brought us a
phone. We were able to use that phone to
tell um our loved ones that we were
still alive. Um
yeah, and it was winter and you know,
cobble winters are really cold. Uh
initially we didn't have blankets or you
know mattresses or any kind of uh
heaters. Um
so
I I was wearing this jacket that was it
was a red jacket. It was really warm and
I never took that off for the 105 days
and it never got washed. By the end of
it, it looked great.
>> Yeah. Like it could get up and walk away
on its own too.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, uh, that jacket was a
lifesaver.
>> Wow. Um, last question for you is is
tell us about your release, how it was
negotiated, how it was implemented, how
did that happen?
>> So, there were many different uh false
agreements that happened and then it
didn't go through. what Taliban wanted.
They didn't want anything in my return
except they were like, "We just want
American diplomats to come to
Afghanistan, shake hands with the
Taliban, and we'll release him." That
was it. And what they wanted to show is
legitimacy. So that whole plan uh when
the the special on the special
presidential envoy was um uh going to
come to Afghanistan to um for that and
get me take me uh back. So they did the
whole planning. They sell sent like a
whole troop of Navy Seals to Pakistan
with helicopters and everything so that
if anything went wrong they could inter
uh intervene and um carry out a rescue
mission uh for the uh special envoy.
Well, what happened 5 days before he was
supposed to come to Afghanistan is
Taliban basically announced that
everywhere in the country, girls above
grade fifth couldn't go to school. So,
America was basically like, "Oh, we
can't go now." So, they the the
administration walked back. And then we
had a 40minute long call with Wendy
Sherman and uh Nita Loey uh uh Nita Loi
Wendy Sherman several other senators
from the US called the administration
and basically compelled them to
uh carry out the mission and not walk
back. Well, what happened is the special
envoy couldn't come at that time. It
couldn't be uh it couldn't be a public
visit. So, ironically, what happened is
the CIA station chief from Doha decided
to come and what happened, what their uh
intention for that visit was to
establish a relationship with the
Taliban intelligence, CIA and Taliban
intelligence, so they could cooperate uh
in in eradicating ISIS. And you know,
that relationship is still there to this
day. You get little bits and pieces of
it in the media every once in a while.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. So that relationship that that
started because of my uh release is
still which is I find I didn't know
about this but uh it was uh leaked in
New York Times uh by whoever it was
leaked that the CIA station chief came
to uh get me out of Afghanistan.
>> What a story. Well, glad you're back
here. uh tell us where people can can
find more information about the work
that you're doing.
>> So the organization I run is called
Human First Coalition and we actually
run a school for girls in Afghanistan
and we also continue to provide
humanitarian aid. Uh we can't do it to
the same level that we used to do. Uh
but we are trying to start more schools
for girls education. That's our goal
now. Um and human firstcoalition.org or
uh is a nonprofit and uh anyone can find
it on the internet.
>> Any thoughts of going back to medical
school?
>> I think that's uh too far in the in in
the past. Uh I I think I that that ship
has sailed. You know, I grew up on Top
Gun and I wanted to be a fighter pilot
and uh what I what the goal was I was
going to become a doctor and Navy has
this program called a flight surgeon.
Yes. is you basically you are a doctor
but also you go to Florida and you learn
how to be a pilot. So you are both a
doctor and a pilot.
>> That was the goal.
>> It it's it's great but I think uh that
ship has sailed.
>> That's okay. You're doing very very
important work. Safi Raou, thank you so
much for joining us.
>> Thank you. Thank you for having us.
>> And ladies and gentlemen, thank you for
uh tuning in to another episode of Deep
Focus. We we love having these
conversations. We could only do it
because of you. thanks to you. So please
like, share and most importantly
subscribe. We appreciate it very much.
All the best.